Mecca, Islam's holiest city. It was here
on August 7th, 2026, that Saudi Crown
Prince Mohammad bin Salman, Turkish
President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, and
Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif
signed a mutual defense pact.
Each signatory brings a different
strategic asset to the table. Saudi
Arabia has enormous financial resources
generated by oil exports, as well as
crucial geographic position between the
Persian Gulf and the Red Sea.
Its standing is reinforced by the Saudi
monarch's role as custodian of Islam's
two holy mosques, giving the kingdom
unique prestige across the Muslim world.
Pakistan, meanwhile, fields an army of
more than half a million personnel and
is the only Muslim-majority country with
nuclear weapons.
Turkey also commands a large military,
the second largest in NATO by personnel,
and has built a powerful, increasingly
innovative defense industry best known
for its drones. Geographically, it also
straddles two continents, Europe and
Asia.